Today I'm going to share some tips and
techniques for creating vintage badge
logos. This popular design style is
based on the way brand identities were
created in previous centuries with
handlettered layouts that clearly
describe the company, unlike modern logo
designs of today that are condensed into
a simple icon graphic. I'll show you how
Illustrator's vector tools can help you
create interesting vintage style logos,
combining text effects and shapes to
build the layout. My artwork will be
based on a fictional 19th century denim
workware brand called Hamilton's.
Similar to the early days of Levis's or
Carheart, but this vintage style has
become popular for all kinds of logos,
packaging, and t-shirt designs. With
vintage style designs relying so heavily
on wording rather than imagery, it's
important to use fonts that
authentically replicate old hand
lettering. I'm using the Milktore
collection of fonts by my friends at
Heritage Typco. This all-in-one kit not
only includes five fonts with an
authentic handcrafted look that
perfectly complement each other, it also
provides 18 ready-made logo templates,
over 30 vector graphics, and a series of
textures to add the finishing touch to
your work. It contains everything you
need to create vintage style logos,
badges, labels, packaging or title
designs with a handcrafted vibe. I've
teamed up with Heritage Type Co to offer
Spoon Graphics subscribers 10% off.
Follow the link in the description and
use the code spoon of milk 20 during
checkout to secure the best price around
to create your vintage badge logo.
Create a new document in Adobe
Illustrator. The artboard can be any
size. I prefer to then go to view and
hide artboards to give myself plenty of
space to work with.
Begin laying out the name of your brand
with a type tool. The Milktore font
collection contains five perfectly
pairing type faces. Number one is a
lovely brush script. Each font is also
supplied in clean, rough, and textured
variants. Use the basic clean version,
and stick around till the end and I'll
show you an easy way to add extra
roughness and texturing effects
separately.
These prograde fonts are also packed
full of alternate and stylistic
characters. Place the cursor at the end
of the word, then open the glyphs panel.
Test out the various swooshes and
swashes to find an underline that suits
your wording. This single piece of text
already looks like hand lettering rather
than being typed out using a font.
To further customize the text, click the
little envelope distort icon in the top
toolbar. Choose the rise option and set
the bend value to 20%.
Use the type tool to add some additional
text to the logo layout. This time, use
one of the other font styles.
Set the center paragraph style and
adjust the character size and line
height values to set up the text. Then
make any necessary kerning adjustments
by placing the cursor and using the left
and right keyboard keys while holding
Alt to adjust the individual letter
spacing.
Add an arc effect to this text using the
same 20% bend.
Align the two text elements up
centrally.
Add more text elements, this time using
a different font. This collection makes
it easy to match font styles without
needing to find or buy additional
styles.
This time, let's decorate the text with
a shape element. Draw a rectangle to
surround the text. Then, right click and
choose arrange center back to place it
underneath the text.
Change the text to white to make it
visible against the black rectangle.
Select both elements and align them up.
The comma in this wording offsets the
vertical alignment slightly so it's
nudged into place optically.
Envelope distort effects can still be
added to combinations of text and shapes
even though the icon is no longer there
in the top toolbar. Instead, go to
object, envelope distort, and make with
warp. This time, try out the flag
effect.
Add more text elements elsewhere on the
artboard. We'll fit this wording inside
a diamond shape. So, draw a square, then
rotate it by 45°.
Go to object, transform, and scale.
Check non-uniform and enter 300% for the
horizontal value.
Place the diamond on top of the text and
go to object envelope distort make with
top object. But notice how the text is
being warped out of shape too much. Undo
the effect. Then make a copy of the
diamond shape to save it for later.
Use the rectangle tool to draw a
straight edge covering the point of the
diamond. Alt and drag a copy to the
other side. Then shift and click to
select them both. Make a compound path
via the right click menu.
Add the diamond to the selection and
center up the shapes. Then click the
minus front button from the pathfinder
panel to punch out the shapes, leaving
two straight edges on either side of the
diamond. Repeat the envelope distort
effect and notice the text fits
perfectly into the shape.
Go to edit and paste in back to replace
the original diamond shape we copied to
the clipboard. Currently the text is
black on black. So, right click and
choose isolate selected group to adjust
the original text element. Give it a
white fill.
Exit back out to the top layer by
clicking the arrow icon in the top left
corner of the screen. Increase the
border around the text by adding a black
stroke to the diamond shape. Set the
alignment to outside. Then adjust the
size to suit.
A little star graphic makes a nice
detail. Set it up with a white fill and
no stroke. Then move it into place.
Alt and drag a copy to the other side
and group them.
Hold shift and add the diamond to the
selection. Then give it an extra click
to make it the key object so it doesn't
move out of place.
Align the shapes up so they sit
perfectly centrally.
Group all the objects that make up this
piece of text. Then scale and position
it within the logo layout.
Vintage logos can be layouts of text or
contained within outlining shapes. Let's
make this design a circular badge by
drawing a circle around the design,
overlapping each end of the script
slightly.
Give this circle a black stroke with an
appropriate weight.
Find the scissors tool, then snip the
path and delete the unwanted portions
that overlap the script text.
Draw another circle that's slightly
larger. Clear it stroke, leaving an
invisible path. Select the type on a
path tool and click to type around the
circle.
Add some more wording to the design in
one of the milk store fonts.
Center it up at the top by dragging the
little alignment widget with the direct
selection tool.
Altering a font's tracking value to
space out the letters is a great way to
fill up the available area without
having to make the actual text size too
big.
Copy and paste in front a duplicate of
this type on a path shape. Then edit the
wording. Rotate the circle by 180° to
place the text on the bottom. Then
adjust the alignment handle with the
direct selection tool to place the text
the right way up.
While the text is now readable, it's set
to the inside of the path. An easy fix
is to adjust the baseline shift value to
offset it to the outside of the path.
Draw another circle to outline the
design. A trick to line it up centrally
is to turn on outline mode from the view
menu or the command and Y shortcut.
Alt and drag the shape from the center
point. Then turn off outline mode again.
Copy and paste this outlining circle to
add another slightly larger border. This
time with a much broader stroke.
As one last finishing touch, add another
star graphic to fill out the empty
space. This portion of the layout is
part of the type on a path area. So,
rotate the star to follow the circular
outline.
Select the rotate tool, then turn on
outline mode. Click the center point,
then alt and drag a duplicate star. The
pivot point will follow the rotation to
keep the star lined up perfectly. Use
the command and D shortcut or control
and D on Windows to repeat the step one
more time to create three stars.
Select all three then go to object
transform and reflect. Hit copy to
generate a flipped set for the other
side.
Make any adjustments to the logo layout
and draw a selection across everything
and drag a duplicate off to one side.
We'll keep a live backup. We process the
duplicate to permanently apply all the
effects and turn it into a completely
vector outline. To prevent the original
objects from being selected, go to
object lock selection. Then turn back on
the view artboards option so the design
is seen against the gray backdrop.
Draw a selection around the duplicate.
Then go to object and expand appearance
followed by objects and expand to apply
all the envelope distort effects and
convert the text and strokes to
outlines.
Ungroup the objects. Then select a black
filled element. Go to select same and
fill color. Merge all these shapes into
one outline by clicking the unite option
in the pathfinder panel. Also turn it
into a compound path under the object
compound path and make menu. This is
required for an upcoming step to ensure
the pathfinder tool works correctly.
Right click and choose arrange center
back to make the white elements visible.
Then repeat the process for these
objects. Select same filler color unite.
Make a compound path.
Add the black objects to the selection
along with the white objects. Then click
the minus front button in the pathfinder
panel to punch out the shapes leaving a
continuous outline.
There's an easy way to add some cool
texturing effects to your vintage logo.
That's by downloading my free ink stamp
texturizer from Spoon Graphics by
following the link in the description.
Double click the smart objects layer and
paste in your logo to replace the
placeholder. Save and close the PSB to
find your logo processed with cool ink
bleed and texturing effects.
You can change the color if necessary or
play with the texturing options to find
the best spread of details.
If you want to learn how to create these
effects yourself, check out my video
titled How to Create a Distressed Letter
Press Print Effect in Photoshop.
The final result is a vintage logo with
a neat layout of text elements, all
contained within a circular outline to
create a badge style brand design. The
Milk Store font collection made font
pairing easy with the five expertly
designed type faces included in one kit.
Then with the help of a few of
Illustrator's tools and effects, it's
all combined into an authenticl looking
vintage logo design. If you enjoyed this
tutorial or learned new tips and tricks,
a thumbs up on the video would be really
appreciated. Stick around for more of my
content by subscribing to the channel
and be sure to join my mailing list at
Spoon Graphics to download all my free
design resources. As always, thank you
very much for watching and I'll see you
in the next one.